This is the third exam of the astronaut selection process.
なんば　むった
うちゅう　ひこうし
せんばつ
(南波六太)＜宇宙飛行士を選抜
する第３次試験➡
へいさ
閉鎖ボックスでの生活が
続く中＞
As we continue life in the sealed box...
Oops.
ふくだ
(福田)おっと｡
ふるや
(古谷)おう おっちゃん｡
Hey, old timer...
Eh?
All the better for us.
おれ
(古谷)俺らにとっては
好都合なことやろ｡
うん…まあ…そうだけど…➡
Well, that's true...
何か あれだろ？
楽しめないだろ これじゃ｡
But you know...
It's no fun this way.
＜福田さんは宇宙飛行士の
ぼしゅう
募集が発表された時➡
When JAXA announced the astronaut selection exam,
公正を期すためか ロケット開発の
じにん
仕事をすぐ辞任したという＞
Fukuda immediately quit his job with the rocket development program.
《辞めるか？普通…｡➡
Who would quit their job?
ホンマ アホやわ》
He's such a fool...
I will rise,
climb,
and shoot through the atmosphere
My goal is zero gravity
Space Brothers
Waves of people flood the intersection
Like vague silhouettes they stream past incessantly
How do I look in their midst?
I don't know
Hiding my true intentions desperately
I dish out vague excuses
My ambitions of going to space, harbored for so long,
are frail and brittle
No matter how I turn the globus
I have no home where I end up
There's no point to looking on a map
I will rise,
climb,
and shoot through the atmosphere
until I can look down on the entire world
I will yell
and scream
with a heart of steel
that I am going to zero gravity
Please order Fukuda new glasses.
#15 Let's Talk About Space
Really? Furuya did?
Please order Fukuda new glasses.
ほしか
(星加)なるほど 古谷君がね｡➡
Please order Fukuda new glasses.
でも口で言えば早いのに
なんで紙？
But wouldn't it would have been faster to make the request verbally?
はらだ
(原田)さあ わかんないですけど
照れくさいからとか？
Yes, I don't know why he did that.
Maybe he was embarrassed.
(星加)で 茄子田さんには？
(原田)まだ見せてないです｡➡
Have you told Nasuda?
I haven't shown it to him yet.
今日 午後から来るんで｡
He'll be here this afternoon.
(原田)理事長なんていうかな？
What do you think the director will say?
｢もうちょっと様子が見たい｣
とか言いそうじゃないですか？
I can see him telling us to wait and see a little longer.
(星加)いや 大丈夫だよ｡
No, it's okay.
めがね
至急 福田さんに新しい眼鏡を｡
Order Fukuda new glasses right away.
Ah... Right.
あっ…はい！
古谷君の気持ちを尊重しよう｡
We should respect Furuya's wishes.
つるみ
つか
交代だ 鶴見｡お疲れさん｡
We're here to relieve you, Tsurumi.
Good work.
(鶴見)これ見ろよ 星加｡
初日の｢時間当てクイズ｣｡
Look at this, Hoshika.
It's from when we asked them the time.
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ]乗った時と降りる時に➡
I checked the odometer when I boarded and exited the bus.
走行メーターを
チェックしたんだよね｡
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](古谷)なんやて!?
Hold on!
走行メーター？
おかしいだろ？
The odometer...
It doesn't make sense, right?
あの位置からメーターは見えない｡
He couldn't have seen the odometer from that angle.
(鶴見)バスのカメラに
しっかり映ってたよ｡➡
The camera on the bus caught everything.
南波君だけが
確実に あの時計を見てる｡➡
Nanba was the only one who looked directly at the clock.
君がワザと｢隠さずに見せよう｣
といった時計をね｡
The clock you said to openly display.
いす
ハハハ さすが椅子のネジにも
気付いた男だ｡
Can't say I'm surprised, as he also noticed the loose screw.
Screw!
ところが彼は時計を
見たことを隠してウソを言った｡
However, he concealed that fact from the others.
これは どう評価すべきなのか｡
How should that influence his score?
君は どう思う？
What do you think?
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ]目つぶっててもスピードは
わかるよ｡俺｡
I can estimate a car's speed, even with my eyes closed.
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](古谷)え～!?
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](せりか)スゴイ！
Eh?
Wow...
とっさのハッタリにしては
計算のつじつまも合ってるし➡
His fabricated story and calculations made sense.
何より他のメンバーが
説得されてる様子がわかる｡
And he was able to convince the other members.
ってことは…｡
Which means...
ウソでも正解だ｡
Lying was the correct decision.
やっぱりね｡
I thought you might say that.
じゃ 後半戦 頼んだよ｡星加｡
Well, the second half is all yours, Hoshika.
(星加)おう｡
Yeah.
使うんだろ？緑のアレ｡
You're going to use the green ones?
仕事ですから｡
That's my job.
(古谷)南波～➡
Nanba!
次 自分の番や テレビ電話ルーム｡
おう｡
It's your turn to use the video phone room.
Right...
＜我々の体調を見るため➡
In order to monitor our health,
毎日１回は医師による
もんしん
個人問診がある＞
JAXA has a doctor examine us once a day.
南波で～す｡
よろしくお願いしま～す｡
This is Nanba.
It's a pleasure.
＜唯一 見られる
メンバー以外の顔は➡
The only time I get to see a face that doesn't belong to a teammate
かんせい
管制室にいる…➡
is when I see
この医師の顔なのだ＞
the doctor down in the control room.
(医師)やあ｡
Hello.
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](医師)おやおや 南波君は
わかりやすいねぇ｡
Oh, Nanba is very easily recognizable...
(医師)私の顔を見た時の
テンションの波具合が➡
Every time you see my face, the graph of your tension level forms a parabola.
きれ～な放物線を描くのよね｡
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ]う…すいません｡
Er, sorry...
あわ
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ]で どうなの？泡立ってる!?
So, how's it going?
Making lots of bubbles?
やっぱ俺の健康基準は
そこですか？
Is that how you determine whether I'm healthy?
(医師)じゃあ 健康だ｡
⦅バブー⦆
Then you're super-healthy.
Bubbly!
(福田)どうも｡
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ](医師)あ～福田さんね➡
Hello.
Ah, Fukuda.
ずつう
目の疲れから頭痛に
なってませんか？➡
Are you getting any headaches from eye strain?
それから肩や腰は どうですか？
Any back pain?
No, I'm still doing fine.
いやあ まだまだ大丈夫ですよ｡
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ]実は いい知らせがあります｡
Actually, I have some good news for you.
Huh?
[ﾓﾆﾀｰ]古谷君からのプレゼント｡➡
A present from Furuya.
パスボックスにあります｡
It's in the pass-through box.
古谷君から？
From Furuya?
福田さん 眼鏡！
Fukuda, you're wearing glasses!
ありがとう 古谷君｡
Thank you, Furuya.
Huh?
何が？俺は なんも言うてへんで｡
What?
I never told them anything.
正～直｡➡
な～んも言うてへん｡
I didn't say a single word.
ピピピピピッ ピピピピピッ…)
みぞぐち
(溝口)《まただ》
There it is again...
(ピピピピピッ ピピピピピッ…)
誰か鳴ってますよ！
Someone needs to turn that off!
《誰だよ こんな真夜中に》
Who would set an alarm for the middle of the night?
ピピピピピッ ピピピピピッ…)
(ピピピピピッ ピピピピピッ…)
(溝口)みんな！１回 起きて！
Everyone, get up!
昨日に続いて今日も！
一体 誰のアラームなんですか!?
That's the second night in a row!
Whose alarm is it?
手島さん…➡
Teshima.
手島さんのベッドの方から
聞こえる気がするんですけどね！
The sound came from your bed.
(手島)あ…俺じゃないよ！
じゃあ 誰なんですか!?
What?
It wasn't me...
Then who was it?
知らないよ！
I don't know!
(北村)私は…違いますよ｡
It wasn't me.
チッ これじゃ昨日の繰り返しだ｡
We're not getting anywhere!
(ケンジ)誰もやってないって
言うんだから➡
Since everyone said they weren't responsible, you should stop being so accusatory.
誰かを疑うのは やめよう｡
《またリーダーぶりやがって》
He's trying to play leader again.
(ケンジ)管制に何度きいても➡
We've asked Mission Control,
｢中での問題は自分達で
解決して下さい｣の一点張りだ｡➡
but they said that we should solve any internal problems.
だから みんなで考えよう
解決策を｡
So let's work together to find a solution.
はんにん
僕は犯人を割り出すのが
解決策だと思いますけど➡
I believe that the solution would be figuring out who's responsible.
この中に いるんでしょう？
It must be someone in this room.
わかった じゃあ こうしよう｡
今日は僕が寝室の通路で寝るよ｡
Okay, how does this sound?
I'll sleep in the bedroom hallway tonight.
アラームが鳴ったら
すぐに音の出所を見つける｡
If an alarm starts ringing, I'll track down the source.
まかべ
ぎせい
真壁さん 自分だけ犠牲になって
正義の味方ですか？
Makabe, are you trying to play good guy by taking one for the team?
これで もし あなたが犯人なら
自作自演で問題解決｡
If you were the responsible party, you'd build yourself up as a hero.
みんなの信頼を得るための
かせ
点数稼ぎと思われても➡
The rest of us have to wonder if you're just trying to score points with the team.
仕方ないですよ｡
わかった じゃあ こうしよう｡
Okay,
how about this?
《クソッ なんで僕が
こんな所で！➡
Damn it!
Why am I here?!
イラだつ！
…いや ちょっと待てよ➡
I'm pissed.
Wait... Hold on.
さっきの会話の流れ…あくまで
しゅどうけん
主導権をとろうとしてる➡
Did Makabe just maneuver me into thinking
僕の考えを見越して 真壁に
ゆうどう
誘導されたんじゃないのか？➡
that I was leading that discussion?
僕をこんな通路で寝かせて
さらにストレスを与えるために》
So he could trick me into sleeping in the hallway and stress me out?
《真壁…》
Makabe...
(ケンジ)《やっぱり２人を
選出する方法を➡
Was it a mistake to use a point system
点数制にしたのが
間違いだったんじゃないか？➡
to decide who'll be chosen?
みんな自分の点数ばかり
気にして➡
People are starting to bicker
互いに争う形になってきてる➡
because they're worried about their scores.
And now we have this alarm mess.
そこへきて このアラーム騒動➡
どうしたら いいんだ？》
What should I do?
Everyone! Hey, it's gone!
(古谷)みんな ちょっ ないで！
なくなってるで！➡
It's missing!
Wake up! Hey!
起きてって！なぁ！
早よ 早よぅ！
Hurry up!
にった
(新田)朝から うるせ～な｡
You're so damn loud...
おはよう｡
ふああ～｡
Good morning.
何がないって？
時計や！時計！
What's missing?
The clock!
ロッカーの上にあったヤツ！
The one that was above the lockers!
(古谷)≪とにかくベッドから
出てこいや！≫
Just get out of bed!
何いってんだよ｡
なくなるワケないだろ？
(古谷)ウソちゃうわ！
What are you talking about? How could the clock be missing?
I'm not lying!
おはようございます｡ん？
Good morning...
Oh...
あっ時計がない！
The clock is gone!
ないね…｡
だから言うたやろ！
It really is gone.
That's what I said!
時計なら昨日
お前らが使ってただろ？
Didn't you use the clock yesterday, during that handstand contest?
逆立ち対決で｡
それなら私が戻しましたよ｡
I put it back up there after we were finished...
終わった後ここに｡
(古谷)でも あらへん！
But it isn't there!
とりあえず管制に聞いてみるよ｡
Let's ask Mission Control first.
ああ こちらＡ班 福田です｡
Hello, this is Fukuda, from Team A.
えっとですね｡ロッカーの上に…｡
探すか｡
So, the clock above the locker is...
Let's look around.
Yeah.
あれなかったら 全く時間
分からんくなるで｡
We'll lose track of time without a clock.
何しとんねん！
What are you doing?
さすがに ないか｡
Not in here, of course.
あ…はい｡了解しました｡
Huh?
Oh, yes.
Understood.
なんだって？
それが…➡
What'd they say?
We're supposed to resolve any internal problems.
｢中で起こった問題は
自分達で解決するように｣って｡
あの…！
Um...
見つけたんですけど…！
冷蔵庫の上に｡
I found it.
On top of the fridge...
(古谷)なんや これ…！
(新田)ひでえな｡
What the hell?
That's pretty ugly.
誰や？
Who was it?
こんなことしたヤツ！
Who the hell did this?
誰や？
こんなことしたヤツ！
Who was it?
Who the hell did this?
Was it really one of us?
いるんですか？
この中に｡
みなさん おはようございます｡
Good morning, everyone.
パスボックスに
新しい課題を入れておきました｡
A new task has been placed in the pass-through box.
１５分以内に準備して下さい｡
You have fifteen minutes to prepare.
(古谷)これじゃ その１５分も
わからんけどな｡
We can't even tell when fifteen minutes are up.
それでは
箱のフタを開けて下さい｡
Please remove the lid from the box.
Whoa.
うわっ！…白いパズル｡
A-A white jigsaw puzzle...
何や これ!?全部白？
What the hell?
The pieces are all white?
完成しても…白｡
So when the puzzle is finished, it's completely white?
Uh...
え～っと 説明が書いてある｡➡
There are instructions.
180ピースの長方形
制限時間３時間だって｡
This is a 180-piece rectangular puzzle.
The time limit is three hours.
《絵がなきゃ １個ずつ
当てはめていくしか方法はない》
If the puzzle doesn't form a picture, we'll have to try each piece individually.
それでは…始めて下さい｡
Now, then...
Please begin.
What is this supposed to test?
《こんなことで
何がわかるってんだ》
《思ったより時間食うな…》
This is taking longer than I expected.
《くそっ！残り時間がわからん》
Damn, I have no idea how much time is left.
誰やねん…時計壊したヤツ｡
Who broke the clock?
Come clean...
正直に言えや｡こんなん時間配分も
できへんっちゅうねん！
We've lost track of time now.
俺はてっきり 古谷がまた
踏み壊したと思ったけどな｡
I assumed you accidentally stepped on something again.
Eh?
事件は 第一発見者が
怪しいってもんだぜ｡
The first person on the scene is the most suspicious.
《こいつ…》
Damn you.
そういう自分は どうやねん！
Then how about you?
《空気悪い…》
It's really tense in here...
古谷君｡
Furuya.
この課題なら 時計がなくても
やることは変わらないよ｡
A clock wouldn't help us complete this task.
ちゃうねんて おっちゃん｡
俺が気に入らんのは➡
That's not it, old timer!
I'm mad because someone in this room is lying!
この中に 嘘つきがおるって
ことやねん！
ズバッと言うけど…
場所知ってたから➡
I'll be blunt.
Itou, did you find the clock so quickly because you hid it?
すぐに見つけたんちゃうの？
伊東さん！
えっ！私!?
Huh? Me?
怪しい点が多いねん｡今朝だって
１人だけすでに作業着姿やったし｡
There are more than enough reasons to suspect you.
You were the only one awake and dressed this morning.
Oh, good morning.
⦅おはようございます…ん？⦆
俺より早起きしてたワケやろ？
何で時計に気付かへんねん｡
You were awake before I was.
Why didn't you notice the missing clock?
U-Um...
えっ…え～っと…｡
《逆立ちの練習に
夢中だったからです》
Because I was too focused on practicing my handstand.
それに 時計捜す時
自分 イスの上に登ってたけど➡
Plus, you got on a chair to look for it.
あんな物の捜し方あるか？
不自然やと思うわ｡
Why would you think to use a chair?
That was very odd.
私は昔から部屋での捜し物は…
あんな感じで…｡
I always do that when I'm looking for something...
自分が犯人か？
Huh? What now?
Are you responsible?
I...
《私は…➡
I know who the culprit is.
私は犯人を知っている》
なあ…｡
Hey...
Guys...
みんな…｡
宇宙の話をしよう｡
Let's talk about space.
I heard that Brian Jay had a daughter, Teshima.
ブライアン･ジェイには 一人娘が
いたらしいですよ 手島さん｡
(手島)え？そうなんだ…｡
Oh, really?
(溝口)かわいそうすぎますよね｡
I feel sorry for her.
その娘さんも見たのかな？
あの映像｡
Did his daughter see that footage?
(ﾏｲｹﾙ)⦅ダメだ！機体が回転して
全く安定しない！➡
It isn't working...
The capsule's spinning out of control!
終わりだ ちくしょう！⦆
We're done for!
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅落ち着け マイケル！
できることはやろう｡➡
Stay calm, Michael!
Just do what you can!
今後の事故調査で
きっと役に立つ⦆
The data from this accident will be very useful.
見たと思いますよ｡
他人の僕らが見てるんだから｡
She must have,
given that they showed us, and we're total strangers.
Did you hear that, Makabe?
《聞いているか 真壁…》
《声はギリギリ
君に届くトーンだ｡➡
I was speaking in a voice just loud enough for you to hear.
丸聞こえの会話より
こっちの方が気になるだろう》
Which is more likely to catch your attention than if I spoke really loudly.
アポロとかスペｰスシャトル時代の
宇宙飛行士って➡
During the Apollo and space shuttle eras,
ほとんど皆
家族持ちだったじゃないですか｡➡
the astronauts all had families.
今みたいに ２０代の
独身宇宙飛行士が➡
Unlike today, when far more astronauts in their twenties are young and single.
飛ぶことなんて少なかったし｡➡
でも これからの
火星ミッションじゃ➡
But there will probably be more single astronauts for the Mars mission,
さらに独身の飛行士は
増えると思うんですよね｡➡
地球に残す心配事は
少ないにこしたことはないし｡➡
since they won't have to worry about leaving anyone back on Earth.
自分の子供の身に
何か起こっても➡
And if anything happened to your child,
地球まで助けに
戻れないですからね｡
you couldn't return to Earth to help.
《アラームのお返しだ 真壁｡➡
This is payback for the alarm, Makabe.
少しずつ脳裏に焦燥感を
植えつけてやる》
I'll slowly plant these fears in your mind.
⦅じゃあ ３次試験に
行ってくるよ⦆
Well, I'm off for the third exam.
(ユキ)⦅いってらっしゃい⦆
Have a safe trip!
(風佳)⦅かぺ～！⦆
Ka-pe!
宇宙の話をしよう｡
Let's talk about space.
僕達は宇宙飛行士になるんだから｡
犯人探しは 探偵の仕事です｡
We're trying to become astronauts, so let's leave solving mysteries to detectives.
You didn't have to stand up to say that.
わざわざ起立して言うなや｡
学級委員長か！
Are you supposed to be a class rep?
Cla—
《学級委員長…》
Class rep?
(古谷)はい 着席～｡
Okay, take a seat.
やっさん｡
(古谷)なんや？
Ya...
What's up?
ここは どこだ？
Where are we?
Huh?
ここは どこだ？
Where are we?
自分 頭 大丈夫か？➡
Are you all right in the head?
んなもん ＪＡＸＡの試験会場に
決まっとるやろ｡
We're in the middle of a JAXA exam.
ブー！ハズレ｡
Wrong.
What?
ここは…宇宙だ｡
We are
in space.
やっさん もっと
宇宙飛行士気分でいこうぜ｡
Ya, we should act more like astronauts.
ＪＡＸＡの人が宇宙の窓を
つけてくれたのは そのためだよ｡
That's why JAXA designed the windows to look out into the stars.
ここは宇宙船で 俺らは飛行士｡
We're pilots on a spaceship.
時計は大事だけど もっと大事
なのは 俺らの感覚じゃねえの？
The clock is important,
but our own sense of time is more important.
１日が２４時間っていうのは
地球だけの話ですもんね｡
A day is only twenty-four hours on Earth.
確かに｡火星の１日は
地球より３９分長い程度だけど➡
Actually,
on Mars, a day is thirty-nine minutes longer.
月の場合は
約656時間もあるもんな｡
But on the moon, a day lasts six hundred, fifty-six hours.
逆にＩＳＳに乗ってたら
４５分毎に昼夜が変わるし｡
But if you're on the ISS, day and night flip every forty-five minutes.
宇宙に出たら
時間の概念は変わるよ｡
Once we're in space, our concept of time will adjust.
なんか…話 流れてへんか？
Are you trying to change the subject?
いやいや これが本筋だって｡
Not at all.
This is very relevant.
宇宙に出て 火星に向かう船の
時計がぶっ壊されたとするよな｡
Let's pretend we're on a spaceship to Mars, when the clock breaks down.
そん時 宇宙飛行士の
俺らはどうするか｡
As astronauts, how do we react?
それを見るために
ＪＡＸＡの人が壊したんだよ｡
In order to learn the answer,
あの時計を｡
JAXA broke the clock.
Let's act like that's what's happening.
そういうことにしとこう｡
星加さん 不思議ですね
南波君って｡
Hoshika, Nanba is a mystery.
Yeah...
彼は今 頭の中で
いろいろ考えてるんだろうな｡
He must have a lot on his mind right now.
《ＪＡＸＡの人が忍び込んで
壊したってのはないな｡➡
JAXA wouldn't have sent someone to sneak in and break the clock.
If Nanba's theory were true, they could have just taken away the clock.
南波の言う目的やったら 時計を
回収すればいいだけの話やろ》
《それぐらい南波でも…あっ！》
Nanba should know that...
《まさか…➡
Could it be?
南波が犯人か！》
Did Nanba do it?!
《俺の目は ごまかされへんぞ…》
You can't fool me...
《わからない…➡
I don't get it...
このパズルみてえに
頭ん中 真っ白になりそうだ》
I'm drawing a complete blank, as blank as this puzzle.
《できれば 俺が言った通り
JAXAの人が犯人ならよかった》
If only my theory were true and JAXA were responsible...
⦅あっ…！⦆
⦅はぁ はぁ…⦆
《どうして あんな事したんだ…》
Why did you break the clock,
《福田さん…》
Fukuda?
The lens inside my eyes
went completely out of focus when I saw you
The signs of love flooded the occipital lobe of my cerebrum
The words the left side of my brain produced
brought my vocal cords to reverberation
Vigorously my confession traversed my tongue
May I love you?
May I really love you?
May I be beside you? (The concentration of my hormones rose)
(Dopamine overwhelmed me)
Can I hold your hand? (My blood circulation powered up)
＜閉鎖環境で時計を壊したのは
福田さんだった＞
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#16 Alarm, but No Clock
Fukuda was the one who broke our only clock in the sealed environment.
＜何で あんな事したんですか？＞
Why did you do that?
(福田)＜もし君が
その理由に気付いたら➡
If you can figure out why I did what I did,
その時は 握手でもしよう＞
＜えっ？どういう意味？＞
I'll shake your hand.
What does that mean?
＜それより どうしよう…
食べ物が足りないみたい＞
Anyway, I don't know what to do.
We're running out of food.
＜私が当番の時
作り過ぎたせいだ＞
It's because I always make too much when it's my turn.
＜壊された時計 そして
睡眠を妨害するアラーム＞
A broken clock,
plus an alarm that interrupts our sleep.
＜閉鎖環境って
事件だらけじゃないか＞
This sealed environment is filled with trial after trial!
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Alarm, but No Clock"
＜それより 食べ物が…＞
What about the food?!
ひびと
(日々人)パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
今週の宇宙写真です！
すっげえ！
This week's space photo!
Awesome!